A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Sir Brian Urquhart FA550
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Affairs Program, Office Files of Sir Brian Urquhart
1986-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Urquhart, Brian
Ford Foundation
FA550
14.46 Cubic Feet 11 record storage boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Records are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Contains correspondence, meeting records, documentation of writing and regional projects, speaking engagements and events, and united nations studies.
Biographical / Historical
Brian Urquhart is a diplomat, author, and World War II veteran. From 1986 to 1995, he served as a Scholar in Residence in the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program.
Urquhart served in the British Army during World War II. After his military service, he helped found the United Nations and became the Personal Assistant of Trygve Lie, the first UN Secretary-General. He helped organize and direct the UN's peacekeeping operations in Cyprus, Kashmir, Lebanon, and the Congo. In 1972, he became the UN's Under-Secretary-General for Special Political Affairs. He stayed in that position until he joined the Ford Foundation.
Arrangement
Arranged in 8 series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Chronological Correspondence, 1986-1995
Series II. Meetings, 1986-1995
Series III. Speaking Engagements, 1986-1995
Series IV. Subject Files, 1987-1995
Series V. Writing Projects, 1986-1995
Series VI. Regional Files, 1986-1995
Series VII. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1986-1995
Series VIII. United Nations Studies, 1986-1995
- Chronological Correspondence, 1986-1995; I; 3.94 Cubic Feet 3 record storage boxes
  - Chrons, 1986 February-March (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1986 April-June (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1986 June-September (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1986 October-December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1987 January-March (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1987 April-June (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1987 July-September (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1987 October-December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1988 January-March (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1988 April-June (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1988 July-September (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1988 October-December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1989 January-March (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1989 April-June (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1989 July-September (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1989 October-December (Box 1)
  - Chrons, 1990 January-March (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1990 April-June (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1990 July-September (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1990 October-December (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1991 January-March (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1991 April-June (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1991 July-September (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1991 October-December (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1992 January-March (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1992 April-June (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1992 July-September (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1992 October-December (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1993 January-February (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1993 March (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1993 April-June (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1993 July-September (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1993 October-December (Box 2)
  - Chrons, 1994 January-March (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1994 April-June (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1994 July-September (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1994 October-December (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1995 January-March (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1995 April-June (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1995 July-September (Box 3)
  - Chrons, 1995 October-December (Box 3)
- Meetings, 1986-1995; II; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Palme Commission -- New Delhi, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Palme Commission, 1986-1993 (Box 4)
  - UNA/UN Panel, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Olaf Palme's Funeral -- Stockholm, 1986 March 15-16 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, 1986 March 21-23 (Box 4)
  - Ralphe Bunche Conference, 1986 May 5-6 (Box 4)
  - UNA Panel, 1986 May 9-10 (Box 4)
  - UNIFIL Workshop -- Oslo, 1986 July 1-4 (Box 4)
  - Keswick/Strathclyde, 1987 May 19-21 (Box 4)
  - Honorary Degree -- Keele University, 1987 June 29-July 3 (Box 4)
  - UNA Panel Lunch, 1987 September 16 (Box 4)
  - BBC Radio Program, 1987 September (Box 4)
  - Carter Center Mediation, 1987 November 4-5 (Box 4)
  - Carter Center -- Middle East Conference, 1987 November 16-18 (Box 4)
  - South Africa/Carter Center, 1988 March 30-31 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, 1988 June 17-19 (Box 4)
  - BBC, 1988 June 20 (Box 4)
  - Brioni, 1988 July 17-22 (Box 4)
  - Martin Wight Memoral Lecture -- London -- Chatham House, 1988 September 27 (Box 4)
  - Berlin-Leiden, 1988 November 20-22 (Box 4)
  - Oslo, 1988 December 11-16 (Box 4)
  - Stockholm, 1989 January 10-11 (Box 4)
  - San Diego, 1989 February 1-2 (Box 4)
  - York University -- Toronto, 1989 March 2 (Box 4)
  - Middle East Development Conference, 1989 March 23-26 (Box 4)
  - John Bright Lecture -- London, 1989 March 28 (Box 4)
  - Ditchley, 1989 May 5-7 (Box 4)
  - IPA -- Briarcliff Manor, 1989 September 19 (Box 4)
  - Copenhagen -- Lund, 1989 October 15-18 (Box 4)
  - IEWSS -- Frankfurt, 1989 October 19-21 (Box 4)
  - International Affairs Program -- Cairo/Jerusalem, 1989 October 23-27 (Box 4)
  - Study Group -- Gorbachev/UN Reform -- Franck: NYU Law School, 1990 January-April (Box 4)
  - IEWSS Annual Conference -- Stockholm, 1990 June 7-9 (Box 4)
  - Fletcher School Symposium -- Defining a New World Order, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Birenbaum -- Reinventing the United Nations, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Pearson Center, 1995 April 24-25 (Box 4)
  - Keystone, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Quebec, 1995 April 6-7 (Box 4)
  - Canada -- Rapid Deployment, 1995 (Box 4)
- Speaking Engagements, 1986-1995; III; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Engagements Fulfilled, 1995 (Box 5)
- Subject Files, 1987-1995; IV; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Aborted BBC Project, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (1/3), 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (2/3), 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Bunche Film (3/3), 1993 (Box 5)
  - Disaster Relief, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Iran-Iraq War Project, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Otunnu Project, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Secretary General Good Offices, 1993 (Box 5)
  - TV Projects, 1989-1995 (Box 5)
  - United Nations TV Project, 1994 (Box 5)
- Writing Projects, 1986-1995; V; 2.63 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Articles, Reviews, Op-Ed Pieces, Lectures, 1986-1989 (Box 6)
  - Articles, Reviews, Op-Ed Pieces, Reviews, Pamphlets (1/2), 1990-1995 (Box 6)
  - Articles, Reviews, Quotes, Prefaces, Introductions, etc. (2/2), 1990-1995 (Box 6)
  - Bunche Materials -- Ford Foundation -- Box Sheets, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- Distribution, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- Report Release, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Study -- "A World in Need of Leadership", 1991 (Box 6)
  - Leadership Studies -- Leadership -- Ambassador's Meeting, 1990 November 20 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Preliminary Letter, 1990 January 26 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Responses to 1/26/90 Letter, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Questionaires/Responses, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Leadership Project, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Studies -- Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Project Meeting -- Uppsala -- New York -- Agenda and Attendance, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Leadership Project Meeting -- Uppsala -- New York -- 4/24 Meeting, 1990 April 24 (Box 7)
  - United Nations -- Emergencies Project -- Correspondence, 1991 (Box 7)
  - United Nations Secretariat Reorganization Project, 1991 (Box 7)
- Regional Files, 1986-1995; VI; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Africa, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Cambodia, 1989-1992 (Box 7)
  - Impact of East-West Tensions on the Third World, 1986-1987 (Box 7)
  - Middle East (1/2), 1986-1991 (Box 7)
  - Middle East (2/2), 1989-1995 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1986-1995; VII; 1.31 Cubic Feet 1 record storage box
  - Ford Foundation -- General (1/2), 1986-1994 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- General (2/2), 1986-1995 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1988 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1989 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1989 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1991 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1991 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1992 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1992 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1993 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1993 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994 July-December (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1995 January-June (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1995 July-December (Box 8)
- United Nations Studies, 1986-1995; VIII; 3.94 Cubic Feet 3 record storage boxes
  - United Nations Current File, 1986-1992 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Dinner, 1987 April 21-22 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Notes and Follow-up, 1987 April 21-22 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Agenda and [illegible], 1987 April 21-22 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Iran-Iraq War Conference -- Invitations and Replies, 1987 April 21-22 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting I -- Proceedings and Follow-up, 1987 July 15 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting I -- Invitations and Acceptances, 1987 July 15 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Papers, 1987 December 7 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Notes, 1987 December 7 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Lebanese Hostage Meeting II -- Invite Letter and Follow-up`, 1987 December 7 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Invitations and Acceptances, 1989 July 11 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Agenda and Attendance, 1989 July 11 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Pike Paper, 1989 July 11 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Cambodia and the United Nations -- Cambodia Notes, 1989 July 11 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Multilateral Challenges, 1989 November 20 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Maintenance of International Peace and Security -- More Ad Hoc Measures or a System?, 1990 May 30 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Prevention and Limitation of Conflict Through Multilateral Means, 1990 June 5 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Global Environmental Change and the Evolution of the United Nations System, 1990 July 11 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- Leadership for the Future I, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - United Nations Ford Foundation Grants, 1991-1993 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Leadership for the Future II, 1991 January 30 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Leadership for the Future III, 1991 March 14 (Box 9)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- The Gulf Crisis -- The Security Council and the Future, 1991 May 9 (Box 10)
  - Advisory Group on United Nations Financing, 1992 (Box 10)
  - United Nations System Study, 1992-1995 (Box 10)
  - Strengthening United Nations Capacity for Preventative Diplomacy, Peace-making and Peacekeeping, 1992 April 7 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Group First Meeting, 1992 September 16 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Group Second Meeting, 1992 October 30 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Congress -- Volker Mailing, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Press Articles on Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Meeting, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Background Papers, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Costs of Project, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Peace-Keeping Training, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- UN, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Advisory Group, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Volcker and Ogata, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Frank Thomas Memoranda and Talking Points, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Other, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Correspondence -- Financing Project Office Memoranda, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Group Comments on Final Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Transmittal/Response/Requests, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group -- Requests for Report, 1993 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Financing Advisory Group Third Meeting, 1993 January 25 (Box 11)
  - Ambassadors Meeting -- United Nations Financing Repair, 1993 May 6 (Box 11)
  - Yale Group -- United Nation's Next Fifty Years, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Volunteer Force, 1977 October (Box 11)